A Finding Aid to the Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr. artists' letters collection, 1794-1938, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr. artists' letters collection
1794-1938
Archives of American Art
McGuigan, Mary K.
AAA.mcgumary
Archival Resource Key
0.6 Linear feet
The collection of artists' letters compiled by Mary and John McGuigan Jr. measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1794-1938. The collection is comprised of a group of letters, writings, and signed documents to and from a variety of artists, art administrators, art critics, historians, and art-related organizations assembled from multiple sources. It also includes associated printed material with some documents and a few photographs, including carte de visites and cabinet cards.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
John F. McGuigan Jr. and Mary K. McGuigan purchased these letters and generously donated them to the Archives of American Art between 2000 and 2019. The McGuigans have purchased and donated additional archival materials to the Archives, including a portion of the Douglas Volk and Leonard Wells Volk papers. In 2017 the McGuigans donated an addition to the Sylvester Rosa Koehler papers, including sixty-nine letters from A. Barry, Truman Howe Bartlett, William Merritt Chase, Timothy Cole, Edward Henry Clement, Cyrus Edwin Dallin, Robert Swain Gifford, George Inness, Anna Lea Merritt, Stephen Parrish, John Sartain, Francis Hopkinson Smith, and Frederic Porter Vinton.
Scope and Contents
The collection of artists' letters compiled by Mary and John McGuigan Jr. measure 0.6 linear feet and date from 1794-1938. The collection is comprised of a group of letters, writings, and signed documents to and from a variety of artists, art administrators, art critics, historians, and art-related organizations assembled from multiple sources. It also includes associated printed material with some documents and a few photographs, including carte de visites and cabinet cards.
Item descriptions included in the container listing were provided by Mary and John McGuigan and illuminate the wide range of artists and types of material represented in the collection. While some of the letters document routine transactions such as responses to requests for information, and transmittals of autographs, others document specific artist commissions and projects, exhibition and financial arrangements, business relationships, family events, and travels. The collection includes documentation of portrait painters, including Chester Harding and Rembrandt Peale; nineteenth century landscape artists and artists of the Hudson River School including Albert Bierstadt, George Henry Boughton, Samuel Colman, Jasper Francis Cropsey, and George Inness; sculptors including Daniel Chester French whose letters include sixty-three letters to Charles Dupuy, the caretaker of French's summer home in Massachusetts; publishers such as Mathew Carey, in letters from John Neagle; and the activities of arts institutions such as the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts.
In addition to those mentioned above, letters and signed documents are from Washington Allston, William Holbrook Beard, Eugene Benson, William Tilden Blodgett, Jr., James Renwick Brevoort, Frederic Edwin Church, James Claghorn, John Singleton Copley, Kenyon Cox, F.O.C. Darley, Joseph DeCamp, Frank Duveneck, John Mackie Falconer, Horatio Greenough, Childe Hassam, Ignaz Michael Marcel Gaugengigl, George Healy, George Hollingsworth, William Morris Hunt, Daniel Huntington, Anna Vaughn Hyatt Huntington, Henry Inman, Hugh Bolton Jones, Thomas Dow Jones, Louis Ashton Knight, Charles Robert Leslie, Will Low, Frederick William MacMonnies, Frank Blackwell Mayer, Samuel F. B. Morse, Erastus Dow Palmer, Rubens Peale, Elizabeth Robins Pennell, Tobias (Toby) Edward Rosenthal, John Singer Sargent, George Henry Smillie, Marie Spartali Stillman, William James Stillman, Henry Ossawa Tanner, Abbott Handerson Thayer, Charles Yardley Turner, Stephen Arnold Douglas Volk, William Walcutt, Henry Antonio Wenzler, Benjamin West, Stanford White, Worthington Whittredge, and others.
The collection also includes a friendship album belonging to William Tilden Blodgett, Jr., with poems, sketches, and botanical watercolors, eight photographs including carte de visites and cabinet cards with images of George Hollingsworth, Thomas Dow Jones, Louis Ashton Knight, Henry Antonio Wenzler, and William Walcutt, and two photographs of a model used by Francis Blackwell Mayer when painting The Burning of the Peggy Stewart.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 1 series.
Biographical / Historical
Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr. are art historians and collectors in Milford, Pennsylvania.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Other Finding Aids
Finding aid available.
Arts administrators; Art critics; Artists; Historians; Peale, Rubens, 1784-1865; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; Palmer, Erastus Dow, 1817-1904; Church, Frederic Edwin, 1826-1900; Colman, Samuel, 1832-1920; Whittredge, Worthington, 1820-1910; Beard, W. H. (William Holbrook), 1824-1900; McGuigan, John F., Jr. (John Fuller); White, Stanford, 1853-1906; Tanner, Henry Ossawa, 1859-1937; Inman, Henry, 1801-1846; Harding, Chester, 1792-1866; Hassam, Childe, 1859-1935; French, Daniel Chester, 1850-1931; Greenough, Horatio, 1805-1852; Copley, John Singleton, 1738-1815; Thayer, Abbott Handerson, 1849-1921; Darley, Felix Octavius Carr, 1822-1888; Neagle, John, 1796-1865; Boughton, George Henry, 1834-1905; Peale, Rembrandt, 1778-1860; Inness, George, 1825-1894; Carey, Mathew, 1760-1839; Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts; Bierstadt, Albert, 1830-1902; Cropsey, Jasper Francis, 1823-1900
- Mary K. McGuigan and John F. McGuigan Jr. Artists' Letters Collection, 1794-1938; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  - Abbot, Agnes Ann, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Missing Title
    Cabinet card photograph of the interior of Abbot's studio.
  - Allston, Washington, circa 1830s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Washington Allston (1779-1843), "Monday, 15th" to unknown. Allston responds that it would be a pleasure to receive a group of people at this studio to see his latest work.
  - Beard, William Holbrook, 1862; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
    William Holbrook Beard, New York, 28 January 1862, to Tallmadge Ewers (1832-1902), Secretary of the Young Men's Association, Buffalo, regarding that he cannot take less money for his painting Bears on a Bender, but will reduce the price of Grimal Kin's Dream, both of which are featured in the Buffalo Y.M.A. exhibition that began on 24 December 1861, also mentions two pictures by Worthington Whittredge (1820-1910), and his preparations for a reception in the Studio Building.
    William Holbrook Beard, New York, 13 March 1889, to Laura Maude Wachschlager. Wachschlager was a young autograph collector and asked Beard to write an introduction to her "illustrious list," but Beard humorously declined through a rather long and mellifluous letter.
  - Benson, Eugene, 1866; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Newburyport, Massachusetts, 27 July 1866, to A. D. Vorce, Hartford, Connecticut. Benson thanks Vorce (who ran an art supply and picture frame store) for his compliments regarding an article that Benson had written about Jean-Leon Gerome (1824-1904). In response to Vorse 's suggestion that Benson write a similar article on William-Adolphe Bouguereau (1825-1905), the painter-critic explains that, while Bouguereau is a great painter, he lacks salient traits, and offers nothing of interest to the artist-critic.
  - Bierstadt, Albert, 1888; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
    New York, 5 November 1888, to Hemy Whitney Cleveland (1836-1907, clergyman and author), Louisville, Kentucky. Bierstadt declines Cleveland 's request to exhibit pictures in Louisville. He cites the primary reason as the recent default of payment by some gentlemen of Louisville for pictures loaned to the Southern Exposition. This, in turn, had caused the collapse of the Art Union (the New York entity that organized the loan exhibition to the Southern Exposition), headed by Enoch Wood Perry (1831-1915). This catastrophe had severe pecuniary consequences for many lending artists, including Bierstadt, who reveals he lost "a thousand dollars out of pocket on the matter."
  - Blodgett, William Tilden, Jr., 1869; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
    William Tilden Blodgett, Jr. (1856-1917), friendship album with poems, sketches, and botanical watercolors, 25 December 1869. Son of William Tilden Blodgett (1823-1875), the New York art collector who was instrumental in founding the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the album was a gift from his cousins Nina and Katy, with amateur sketches and watercolors by Warren Delano III (1852-1920), uncle of President Franklin Delano Roosevelt, Coster Chadwick (1952-1914), T. Macomb, and Marie Richers.
  - Blodgett, William Tilden, Jr., 1869; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Two loose watercolors of a Katydid, a type of grasshopper, and "Indian Moccasin" or Lady Slipper flower, by J. D. Forquet, "Drawn from Nature," in the vicinity of Fishkill, New York.
  - Boughton, George Henry, 1878-1889; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
    George Henry Boughton, Kensington, London, 12 November 1878, to the engraver Andrew Varick Stout Anthony (1835-1906), regarding an illustration for the 1879 edition of Longfellow's The Courtship of Miles Standish, which Anthony will engrave, and also mentions Boughton's new studio and the artists Rossetti and Holman Hunt.
    George Henry Boughton, Maastricht, Holland, 11 October 1881, to the painter and sculptor John Severinus Conway (1852-1925), regarding a tour through Holland and American artists in London including J. A. M. Whistler (1834-1903), Anna Massey Lea Merritt (1844-1930), William Mark Fisher (1841-1923), and William John Hennessey (1839-1917).
    George Henry Boughton, 13 April 1885, to Laura Maude Wachschlager. Re: Boughton enclosed signatures from Robert Browning and Edwin Austin Abbey, "Mr. Abbey never signs his full name to me-only 'Ned," for her collection. George Henry Boughton, 13 April 1885, to Laura Maude Wachschlager. Re: Boughton enclosed signatures from Robert Browning and Edwin Austin Abbey, "Mr. Abbey never signs his full name to me-only 'Ned," for her collection.
  - Brevoort, James Renwick, 1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Yonkers, New York, 29 March 1915, to the editor of the Art Annual. In response to the editor's query, Brevoort will need a few days to have a photograph made of himself to satisfy her request.
  - Chester, Joseph Lemuel, 1858; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Joseph Lemuel Chester, prominent genealogist, Washington, DC, 15 May 1858, to Benson J. Lossing (1813-1891), eminent historian and art historian. Regarding Chester's efforts on behalf of house guest Rembrandt Peale (1778-1860) to sell Peale's portrait of Washington, all of which had been facilitated by Lossing.
  - Church, Frederic Edwin, 1892; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Frederic Edwin Church, Hudson, 9 February 1892, to Charles Louis Seeger (1860-1943), publisher, exporter, father of poet Alan Seeger and grandfather of folk singer Pete Seeger. Regarding their forthcoming trip together to Mexico, Church's travel arrangements, and their rendezvous in New York City.
  - Cole, Joseph Foxcroft, 1872-1874; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Joseph Foxcroft Cole, Paris, three letters (1872-1874) to Jeremiah Otis Wetherbee (1832-1901), Boston. Wetherbee was a prominent lumber merchant.
  - Colman, Samuel, 1893-1913; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Samuel Colman, New York, 30 April 1893, to an unknown correspondent, regarding a request for a photograph of the artist, to which he answers that there has never been one on the market.
    Samuel Colman, Greenwich, Connecticut, circa June 1902, to the auctioneer Edward W. Kearney (1852-1918), regarding letter of sympathy about the fatal illness of his wife, Anne Lawrence Dunham Colman (1832-1902), who later died on 28 July in Greenwich.
    Samuel Colman, New York, 30 January 1913, to Dr. Isaac Leopold Rice (1850-1915), regarding a request for correspondence from previous presidents of the National Academy of Design, which he admits he has regretfully destroyed.
  - Copeland, Alfred Bryant, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes a carte-de-visite portrait photograph and calling card.
  - Copley, John Singleton, 1794; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    John Singleton Copley, 29 December 1794, to the collector, engraver, and print-seller Sir John Thane (1748-1818), London, regarding written in the third person, Copley requests portraits of Sir Henry Slingsby, Sir Benjamin Rudyard, Sir Henry Deering, and Francis Rowse for his historical picture of Charles I Demanding in the House of Commons the Five Impeached Members, 1782-1795 (National Portrait Gallery, London).
  - Cox, Kenyon, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Kenyon Cox undated draft fragment of a humorous speech regarding the building of the paintings collection at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York.
  - Cropsey, Jasper Francis, 1862; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
    London, 2 January 1862, to Edward William Cooke (1811-80, English landscape and marine painter). Cropsey and his wife accept Cooke's invitation to visit the following Tuesday evening.
  - Darley, Felix Octavius Carr, 1864; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Felix Octavius Carr Darley, New York, 24 December 1864, to the publishers Messrs. Ticknor & Fields, Boston, regarding postponing his illustrations for The Vision of Sir Launfal by James Russell Lowell (1819-1891), in order to join the Army of the Potomac for the purpose of making studies for Civil War pictures.
  - DeCamp, Joseph, and Otho Wiecker Regarding Louis Prang archive, 1911, 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Joseph DeCamp (1858-1923), Boston, 12 January [1911], to Louis Prang (1824-1909). Re: DeCamp has just returned from Philadelphia and requests Prang to send him a stone so that he may draw the commissioned portrait on it.
    Joseph DeCamp, Boston, [25 February 1911], to Louis Prang. Re: DeCamp confirms to Prang that he himself made the drawing on the stone.
    Otho Wiecker [manuscript dealer], Boston, 14 September 1931, to Daniel W. Patterson, New York. Re: Wiecker sends Patterson one of the two above mentioned DeCamp letters to Prang and suggests that Patterson buy the entire Prang archive he has for sale.
    Otho Wiecker, Boston 19 October 1931 to Daniel W. Patterson, New York. Re: Wiecker sends Patterson the second DeCamp letter to Prang and suggests that Patterson buy the entire Prang archive he has for sale.
  - di Cesnola, Count Luigi Palma, 1885; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Count Luigi Palma di Cesnola, Director of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 25 March 1885, on museum letterhead, to Hayden W. Wheeler (1827-1904), founder of a prestigious jewelry firm in Manhattan. Regarding an invitation to join the Museum board. Includes an engraved portrait of Cesnola.
  - Duveneck, Frank, 1898; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Frank Duveneck (1848-1919), Boston, 7 May 1898, to Julia Graydon Sharpe (1858-1939). Re: Duveneck discusses summer teaching schedules with fellow artist Sharpe.
  - Fairman, Gideon, 1813; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Gideon Fairman, Philadelphia, 4 October 1813, to Gorham A. Worth (1783-1856), Cashier of the Farmers and Mechanics Bank, Albany, regarding new bank note designs with small sketch from America's first prominent engraver.
  - Falconer, John Mackie, 1857; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
    New York, 4 May 1857, to Jasper Francis Cropsey (1823-1900), London. Lengthy letter in which Falconer hopes that Cropsey is enjoying England, but regrets that he and Peter Paul Duggan (d. 1861, portraitist and medalist) are both unwell. Informs Cropsey that James B. Windle, Falconer's employer and Cropsey's close friend, has just died. Discusses happenings in New York. Reports on the upcoming exhibition of the NAD, including Edwin White's (1817-77) picture of the First New-England Thanksgiving. Says White will sail for Havre soon; John Frederick Kensett (1816-72) leaves soon for the Upper Missouri; Frederic Edwin Church (1826-1900) and Louis Remy Mignot (1831-70) also leave on the new steamship Vanderbilt. Mentions Cropsey's dealings with English artists such as Myles Birket Foster (1825-99), troubles with John Gilbert (1817-97), and a letter of introduction for the engraver Henry Le Keux (1787- 1868). The Palmer Exhibition has closed. Mentions that Tompkins Harrison Matteson (1813-84) will attend the opening of the NAD exhibition and that some are disappointed with the works submitted by John Thomas Peele (1822-97), including his The Sound of the Shell and Music of the Reeds.
  - Fields, Kate, 1892; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Kate Fields, journalist, prominent literary and arts figure, Washington, DC, 29 April 1892, to John Sartain (1808-1897). Regarding arrangements for Sartain to attend the Art Congress in Washington the following month.
  - French, Daniel Chester, 1898-1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    Daniel Chester French, New York, 22 December 1898, to James Large, Philadelphia, regarding a letter of introduction from French, who had been selected by the will of the late Richard Smith (1821-1894) to erect a statue of General George Gordon Meade (1815-1872) for the Smith Memorial Arch in Philadelphia, in order to meet with family members to gain background and images for his work. Envelope addressed to Mrs. John B. Large, Philadelphia and postmarked 11 January 1899. Also included is a letter of introduction from John B. Gest (1824-1907), President of The Fidelity Insurance Trust and Safe Deposit Company, Philadelphia, 22 December 1898, to James Large, on behalf of French.
    Daniel Chester French, New York, 11 January 1899, to Sarah Wise Meade Large, Philadelphia, regarding a visit on Saturday, 14 January 1899, to Philadelphia to secure details for his statue of General George Gordon Meade (1815-1872) for the Smith Memorial Arch in Philadelphia; also hopes to take in the PAFA Exhibition.
    Daniel Chester French, New York, 24 January 1899, to Sarah Wise Meade Large, regarding acknowledgement of receipt of letters and photographs of General Meade, as well as a print by Thomas Hicks, and informs he has begun to sculpt the statue in clay. Also included are two letters to Mrs. Large, one from her mother (undated), and the other from her son's teacher Robert Anderson of The Episcopal Academy, Lansdowne, Pennsylvania (1911).
    Daniel Chester French, sixty-three typed letters signed on French's own imprinted stationery and two autograph letters signed. New York City, 12 February 1923- 28 March 1931. Written to Charles Dupuy, the caretaker of French's summer home in Massachusetts.
    New York, 8 February 1909, to Henry Wolf (1852-1916, wood engraver, artist, illustrator), New York. French writes that he has given no photographs of the Melvin Memorial (1908, Sleepy Hollow Cemetery, Concord, Massachusetts) for reproduction to anyone except Monumental News, a technical magazine, and thanks Wolf for his appreciation of his work.
    Glendale, Massachusetts, 22 September 1911, to Henry Wolf (1852-1916, wood engraver, artist, illustrator), New York. In response to Wolfs request to reproduce French's statue of Lincoln for Harper's Magazine, the sculptor regrets that he has promised it to Mr. Johnson of the Century Magazine, who saw it in his studio before it was finished. French suggests that Wolf instead reproduce his equestrian statue of General Draper, photographs of which he can show him once he returns to New York.
  - Gaugengigl, Ignaz Michael Marcel, 1903; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Ignaz Michael Marcel Gaugengigl (1853-1932), Boston, 22 February 1903 to Ezra U. Baker. Re: thanks Baker for his payment for his portrait, and will soon send the portrait of his daughter.
  - Gay, Edward, 1883; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Edward Gay, Mt. Vernon, 24 April 1883, to John Elderkin (1841-1926), editor and author. Regarding illustrations for Bayard Taylor's Lars, a previous and forthcoming trip to Norway, and an outstanding commission for Elderkin.
  - Gerhardt, Karl, undated; 1883-1889; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Autograph letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed "Larkin G[oldsmith] Mead." Florence, Italy, 11 June 1883.
    Typed letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed "Abram S. Hewitt." New York, 8 October 1888. On letterhead of Cooper, Hewitt & Co., to Karl Gerhardt, in care of S. L. Clemens, Hartford.
    Autograph note to Mrs. Karl Gerhardt, signed "Mrs. Mackay." Paris, 14 January 1885.
    Typed letter to William Wilson Corcoran, signed by "Franklin P. Gowen." Philadelphia, 29 January, 1885.
    Autograph letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed by "Brander Matthews." New York, 4 January 1886.
    Typed letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed by "[Senator] Wm. E. Chandler." Washington, DC, 25 June 1888. On United States Senate letterhead.
    Autograph letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed by "[Senator] Jos. R. Hawley." Washington, DC, 10 July 1888. On Senate Chamber letterhead.
    Autograph letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed by "J. R. Hawley." Washington, DC, 8 December 1891.
    Autograph letter to Karl Gerhardt, signed by "Laurence Hutton." Princeton, New Jersey, 21 March 1899.
    Autograph letter to Mrs. Karl Gerhardt, signed by "I. E. Mackay." No location or date given.
    Autograph letter to W. S. Chapman, signed by "Karl Gerhardt." No location or date given.
  - Greenough, Horatio, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Autograph letter signed "Horatio Greenough." Two pages (including integral address leaf). [Washington], not dated. Addressed to Benjamin B. French, Commissioner of Public Buildings in Washington, DC.
  - Harding, Chester, circa 1846-1865; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8-11)
    Chester Harding, Glasgow, Scotland, 21 December 1846, to his son Francis "Frank" Skinner Harding (b. 1843), Springfield, Massachusetts, regarding Harding instructs his youngest son to find Glasgow on the map, pens a sketch of a young boy, and inquires if he has been sledding and obeying his aunts.
    [Chester Harding] Margaret Eliot Harding White (1823-1903), Keene, New Hampshire, to her future sister-in-law Julia Norton Delano, 11 March 1863, regarding White, who edited her father's memoirs, writes to her future sister-in-law, about to Mary Francis "Frank" Skinner Harding, to congratulate her and learn more about her.
    Chester Harding, Springfield, Massachusetts, 8 September 1863, to his future daughter-in-law Julia Norton Delano, regarding welcoming her to the family.
    [Chester Harding] Mary Ophelia Harding Krum (1818-1892), Chateaugay Lake, New York, 19 July 1864, to her future sister-in-law Julia Norton Delano, regarding summer house with her family and father, Chester Harding, and catching up.
    [Chester Harding] Mary Ophelia Harding Krum (1818-1892), Springfield, Massachusetts, 11 September 1864, to her future sister-in-law Julia Norton Delano, regarding her travels and her return to St. Louis with her father, Chester Harding, as well as warning that her brother Frank's income, whom she raised, will barely support them after their wedding.